A Finding Aid to the Frederick Carl Frieseke Papers, circa 1870s-1943, 1982, 1996, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Frederick Carl Frieseke papers
circa 1870s-1943
1982
1996
Archives of American Art
Frieseke, Frederick C. (Frederick Carl), 1874-1939
AAA.friefred
Archival Resource Key
0.3 Linear feet
The papers of Impressionist painter Frederick Carl Frieseke measure 0.3 and date from circa 1870s-1943, 1982, and 1996. This small collection contains scattered documentation of Frieseke's life through several biographical items, printed material, photographs of Frieseke and his family, and miscellany.
Biographical / Historical
Impressionist painter Frederick Carl Frieseke (1874-1939) lived in New York and Paris before becoming a leading figure of the second generation of Americans at Giverny, France. Frieseke studied at the Art Institute of Chicago and the Art Students League, New York City. He moved to France in 1898 where he lived until his death in 1939.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Impressionist painter Frederick Carl Frieseke measure 0.3 and date from circa 1870s-1943, 1982, and 1996. This small collection contains scattered documentation of Frieseke's life through several biographical items, printed material, photographs of Frieseke and his family, and miscellany.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of the collection the Frederick Carl Frieseke papers are arranged as one series.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated in 2019 by Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr., art historians and collectors in Milford, Pennsylvania. Material on reels N737 and 2885 were lent for microfilming in 1968 and 1983 by Mrs. Kenton Kilmer (Frances Friseke) and her son Nicholas Kilmer, Frieseke's daughter and grandson.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm (reels N737 and 2885) of a notebook kept by Frieseke containing a pencil sketch, addresses, expenses, and price lists of paintings; a transcript of the notebook made by his grandson, Nicholas Kilmer; writings and reminiscences decorated with sketches by Frieseke; and price lists. Loaned materials were returned to the donor after microfilming and are not described in the collection container inventory.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection was digitized in 2019 and is available on the Archives of American Art website.
Material lent for microfilming on 35mm microfilm reels N737 and 2885 is available at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- France; Corcoran Gallery of Art; McGuigan, John F., Jr. (John Fuller); McGuigan, Mary K.
- Frederick Carl Frieseke Papers, circa 1870s-1943; 1982; 1996; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1, OV 2
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material consists of a copper plate engraving for Frieseke's calling card; his 1902 Parisian residence registration at 6, rue Victor Considerant; his 1939 French declaration of taxes form; and a customs declaration for a silver medal, a letter, and a check sent to Frieseke in Paris by the Corcoran Gallery of Art, presumably for the Corcoran Silver Medal awarded to Frieseke for Girl at Piano exhibited at the Corcoran's 14th Biennial Exhibition of Contemporary Oil Paintings in 1935. Genealogical notes are a list of probable descendants of Frieseke from 1871 to the 1990s, probably compiled and added to the collection by Miriam A. Kilmer, granddaughter of Frieseke, who included a note explaining the provenance of the material.
  Miscellany consists of two war ration books that belonged to Frieseke's wife and daughter.
  Printed material includes an 1896 edition of Shakespeare's As You Like It signed by Frieseke, with a note from Miriam A. Kilmer authenticating the signature, and a list of items with which the book was auctioned; and an exhibition catalog for a 1982 retrospective at Maxwell Galleries Ltd.
  Photographs are of Frieseke, his wife Sarah Anne and daughter Frances, father Herman, sister Edith, and other family members. They include professional portraits, cabinet cards and candid family photos.
  - Biographical Material, 1902-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Frieseke Family Genealogical Notes, circa 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellany, War Ration Books, circa 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Printed Material, As You Like It, Signed by Frieseke, 1882, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Catalog, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, Edith Frieseke, circa 1875-circa 1890s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, Frances Frieseke, 1919-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Oversized photo housed in OV 2
  - Photographs, Frederick C. Frieseke and Family, circa 1880-circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, Herman Frieseke, circa 1870s-circa 1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, Herman Frieseke, circa 1910-circa 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, Sarah O'Bryan and Father, circa 1901-circa 1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, Other Family Members, circa 1870s-circa 1908; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Oversized Photographs, Frances Frieseke and Herman Frieseke digitized with Box 1, Folders 7 and 9, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 2)